<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY appname "InvScatt">
<!ENTITY app "<application>InvScatt</application>">
<!ENTITY appversion "0.1.0">
<!ENTITY manrevision "0.1.0">
<!ENTITY date "March 2011">
]>
<article id="index" lang="en">
  <articleinfo><title>&appname; Manual</title>
    <abstract role="description">
      <para>
        &app; is a program for performing inverse scattering using the Toplitz Inner Bordering method.
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <copyright>
      <year>2011</year>
      <holder>Paul Childs</holder>
    </copyright>
    <author role="maintainer">
      <firstname>Paul</firstname>
      <surname>Childs</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>Foundation for Research and Technology--Hellas</orgname>
        <address>
          <email>pchilds@physics.org</email>
        </address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>&appname; Manual &manrevision;</revnumber>
        <date>17-03-2011</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <releaseinfo>
      Version &manrevision; documenting &appname; version &appversion;.
    </releaseinfo>
    <legalnotice><title>Copyright</title>
      <para>
        Copyright (C)  2011  Paul Childs.
        Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
        under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.3
        or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
        with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
        A copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU
        Free Documentation License".
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>
  <sect1 id="introduction"><title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      For updates please visit <ulink type="http" url="https://www.github.com/pchilds/IS-TIB">InvScatt's Github repository</ulink>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1><title>The File Menu</title>
    <sect2><title>Spectral/Spatial Profiles</title>
      <para>Files are loaded from the file menu by pressing open from the file menu. The data will be loaded into whichever tab (spectral/spatial) is open at the time. The data should be formatted in columns with optional meta information in the top rows (none of which can start with a digit or negative sign). Standard formatting is 3 columns; the first for the domain variable (for spectral data either wavelength in nm or wavenumber in /cm, or metres for spatial data), the second for the magnitude and the third for phase. Variations on this are also possible. E.g. real and imaginary, magnitude only (which will enter a phase of zero) and not having the domain variable (in which case the first and last values will match what is entered in the start and stop values). Once loaded the magnitude and phase profiles will be displayed on the graph.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Saving</title>
      <para>To save a profile, select Save->Data from the file menu. Choose the format of the data and select a file.</para>
      <para>Saving and restoring the session is not currently implemented.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2><title>Printing</title>
      <para>To print a graph, select Save->Graph from the file menu (as opposed to just print from the file menu which is intended for sending a graph to the printer, though does not function yet). Graphs can be printed in .png, .eps or .svg formats. Scalable Vector Graphics (.svg) is a useful format that allows the image to scale without loss of resolution.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1><title>Navigating the Plots</title>
    <para>InvScatt uses a customised set of plotting widgets for displaying data. For further information and/or feedback see the documentation given in its <ulink type="http" url="https://github.com/pchilds/GtkPlot">repository</ulink>.</para>
    <para>The range of the plot can be zoomed in and out (horizontally and/or vertically) according to the zoom mode selected by clicking on the two boxes in the top right corner of each plot. The box on the left controls whether zooming is to be performed in the horizontal direction only (when two dotted vertical lines are shown), in the vertical direction only (when two dotted horizontal lines are shown) or both horizontally and vertically (A dashed rectangle is shown). The range to zoom over is selecting by clicking at one corner/edge and dragging and releasing at the opposite corner/edge. For convenience, zooming can alternately be performed with a single click (if the setting in the left box is toggled until an X is displayed).</para>
    <para>The box on the right controls whether to zoom in or out (arrows pointing out or in respectively). For the case of zooming in, the resultant image displayed in the plot is the image loosely fitted to the bounding click-drag-release box ("loosely" as the plot tries to fit the axes range to sensible power of ten multiples of 1, 2 and 5). For the case of zooming out, the resultant image is a loose fit to the extrapolation of shrinking the original entire plot into the bounding click-drag-release box.</para>
    <tip><title>tip</title>
      <para>If e.g. you wanted to display more range to the top and left of a linear graph then (with zoom out mode set) you would select a bounding box in the bottom right of the plot.</para>
    </tip>
    <para>By selecting Display Properties in the Properties menu other features of the plots can be altered to allow smooth transfer of data results to a publication ready format without the need of an intermediary step of editing figures. Select the tab appropriate to the plot you wish to change and press "Apply" to make a change and "Close" when done. Apart from the title, font and sizes of the axes and their tick label numbers, the colour of each plot can be changed using the colour selection tool.</para>
    <tip><title>tip</title>
      <para>Keep in mind that if the plot is to be published it will be a lot smaller than what is displayed on the screen. Font sizes in excess of 20 points are generally needed to ensure good readability for the end-user. When printing in black and white some colours may not be clearly seen or be readily distinguishable from other colours.</para>
    </tip>
  </sect1>
  <sect1><title>The Spectral Domain</title>
    <para>.</para>
    <para>The spectral profile can be transformed into the spatial profile that produces it. This process makes use of the <ulink type="http" url="http://dx.doi.org/10.1364/JOSAB.24.001451">Toeplitz Inner Bordering Method</ulink> to solve the Gel'fand-Levitan-Marchenko equations on the Zakharov-Shabat coupled mode system.</para>
    <para>In order to perform the transformation first ensure that the values in the properties menu correspond to your spectrum (e.g. whether the data is in dBs and if it is a reflection or transmission spectrum etc., spectrum over k means k as in wavenumber as opposed to wavelength). The units of the spectral variable should be either nm (for wavelength) or /cm (for wavenumber). Select a Start and Stop range to include all the essential features of the spectrum (but ideally filtering out any out of band noise) and set offset to be the 100% reflection/transmission level. Zero padding is applied around the edges of your spectrum so that the Fourier transform may have a finer resolution (increasing this will give you a finer resolution in the spatial domain, but also give more points over which computational errors can accumulate). It is in powers of 2 as this is the sizes where the Fourier Transform runs most efficiently. Select the number of spatial points (also a power of 2) to evaluate the spatial profile over (a length of (2π/dk)2^(N-zp), where dk is the wavenumber resolution of your spectrum, zp is the value entered into the Zero Padding spinner and N is the number entered into the spatial points spinner). This value should be less than the zero padding value, but large enough to give a length significantly longer than the expected device length. Finally press "Solve Inverse" to get the solution.</para>
    <tip><title>tip</title>
      <para>One should note that the coupling constant produced is not the same as that of the paper of Belai et. al. but instead half of it; more in keeping with other papers in inverse scattering theory (e.g. Feced, Zervas and Miguel). In this case our q is of the form q(z)=-iα(z)k<subscript>0</subscript>/2 e<superscript>-iθ(z)</superscript>, where δn(z)/n = 2α(z)cos(κz+θ(z)) and will correspond for the case of uniform gratings with giving the standard form of reflectivity as: R = tanh<superscript>2</superscript>(qL).</para>
    </tip>
  </sect1>
  <sect1><title>The Spatial Domain</title>
    <para>Applying coercion to the differential of the profile and convolution by the spot size are not currently implemented.</para>
    <para>The spatial profile can be transformed into a resultant spectrum by pressing "Solve Direct". This process makes use of the transfer matrix method on the coupled mode equations. Select the range of distances from the graph that will be used (values are set to zero outside this range), a central wavelength/wavenumber, a range over which to calculate and the number of points to generate, then press "Solve Direct".</para>
    <para>A grating transformed by both methods (Inverse scattering and transfer matrix method), will not correspond exactly due to limiting the ranges of calculation, accuracy of the Fourier transformation and accumulation of numerical errors.</para>
  </sect1>
</article>
